MICHELE CLAIBOURN

I am a research director – a senior data scientist, political scientist, community-engaged scholar, and senior administrator – with 20 years of experience teaching, leading, and managing research and data science teams. Recently I've been building and leading Research Data Services⁷ in the UVA Library.

My own work has turned towards action-based research, using the tools of data science to promote accountable governance², make visible racial and other social inequities³, and impact public policy and movement building. I am always interested in opportunities to use my experience and skills towards creating a more economically and socially just world.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Current | 2015

Director, Research Data Services & Social, Natural, and Engineering Sciences

UVA Library, University of Virginia

- · Lead Data Scientist, Equity Center, 2020-present (partial buyout)
- · Faculty Affiliate/Lead Data Scientist, Global Policy Center, 2019-present
- · Co-Director, Community, Policy, Analytics and Strategy Lab, 2018-present

2015 | 2013

Director, StatLab and Research Data Services

UVA Library, University of Virginia

· Associate Director, Data Science Institute, 2014-2016 (partial buyout)

2013

2011

Data Scientist

Weldon Cooper Center for Public Service, University of Virginia

٠

Assistant Professor

Department of Politics, University of Virginia

2004

EDUCATION

2002 | 1996 PhD., Political Science

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Madison, WI

•

B.A, Political Science

Rice University

• Houston, TX

1993 | 1989

♣ TEACHING AND MENTORING

2020 | 2002

Graduate Courses

University of Virginia and University of Oklahoma

Public Interest Data Lab, Saving Lives with Data, Text as Data, Applied Causal Inference, General Linear Models, Linear Models, Applied Time Series, Mixed-Effects Models/Longitudinal Analysis, Introduction to Statistical Analysis



Undegraduate Courses

University of Virginia and University of Oklahoma

Project First Gen +, Research Design & Analysis, The Presidency and the Public, Media & Political Communication, Political Pscyology & Decision Making, Citizen Competence in American Democracy, Introduction to American Politics

CONTACT

- ™ mclaibourn@virginia.edu
- github.com/mclaibourn

in

linkedin.com/in/mclaibourn

See full CV and project portfolio at mclaibourn.github.io.

Leadership

Consult with researchers and design research projects with partners seeking to better understand racial disparities and social structures, and to develop a policy response.

Founded StatLab⁴, a data science consulting service for members of the UVA community where I continue to serve as a senior consultant and to mentor student fellows.

Build a new division of the library enhancing our ability to support the growing data science research community at UVA, recruiting, hiring, and managing a team with diverse skills and talents to meet emerging university research needs.

Supervise a team of 10-12 full-time staff, 3-4 graduate fellows, and research teams across mulitple collaborations on a range of research projects, including work on equity and COVID response in the Charlottesville community, racial disparities in the local child welfare systems, forced displacement events with humanitarian partners, and additional community-oriented and library-directed data science efforts.

2019	Select StatLab Workshops ⁶	
 2013	University of Virginia	
2013	 Six-part series on Data Science in R, Multiple Imputation, Cluster Analysis, Durat Models, Matching Methods, Mixed-Effects Models, Sentiment Analysis, Topic Modeling, Text Classification, Data Wrangling, Linear Modeling 	
2019	REU Mentor	
20.0	School of Data Science, UVA	
	SELECTED WRITING AND PRESENTATIONS	
2019	Charlottesville Foster Care Study ⁷	
	Report to the Charlottesville Department of Social Services	
	· With Charlotte McClintock and the Public Interest Data Lab	
2019	Panel Chair and Moderator	
	Data & Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virgin .	ıa
2019	Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses	
2013	Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia	
	· With Paul Martin	
2016	Congressional Earmarks and the Politcs of Representation	
	Center for the Study of Data and Knowledge, University of Virginia	
	•	
2013	Citizen Participation and Congressional Responsiveness: New Evidence for Why Participation Matters	y
	Legislative Studies Quarterly 38: 59-82	
	· With Paul Martin	
	· With Faul Mai till	
2012	Creating Constituencies: Presidential Campaigns, Selective Mobilization, and the	1e
	Scope of Conflict	
	Political Behavior 34: 27-56	
	· With Paul Martin	
2011	Presidential Campaigns and Presidential Accountability ⁸	
	University of Illinois Press, Series on Democracy, Free Enterprise, and the Ru	le of
	Law	
	•	
2007	The Third Face of Social Capital: How membership in Voluntary Associations In proves Policy Accountability	n-
	Political Research Quarterly 60: 192-201	
	· With Paul Martin	
	With Full Hardin	
2002	Gender Differences in Citizen-Level Democratic Citi-zenship: Evidence from the	1e
 2000	Comparative Study of Electoral Systems	
2000	Presented to the International Political Science Association (2000), the Midv Political Science Association (2001), and the Conference on Comparative Students (2002)	

· 2001 Winner, Sophonisba Breckenridge Award for best paper on Women & Politics,

Midwest Political Science Association Annual Meeting

of Electoral Systems (2002)

· With Virginia Sapiro

Methods and Software

Statistical modeling and data science
R, RStudio, Shiny
Data wrangling and visualization
Stata and SPSS
Text analytics
GitHub and reproducibility
Some Python and SQL
Qualitative methods

Teaching and Writing

20 years of experience teaching statistics and data science methods, applied policy research, and political behavior to undergraduate and graduate students.

Design data workshop series for student and adult learning communities, including recruiting and mentoring instructors, marketing and assessment, and contributing to select topics.

Experienced writer in multiple formats, from university press books and peer-reviewed journal articles, to action-oriented reports for local and state agencies, educational materials, and informal writing.

Skilled in communicating about data, technology, and policy to stakeholders, advocates, and learners.

Trusting

Trusting and Joining: An Empirical Test of the Reciprocal Nature of Social Capital Political Behavior 22: 267-291

· With Paul Martin



- 1: https://data.library.virginia.edu/
- 2: https://commpas.batten.virginia.edu/
- 3: https://virginiaequitycenter.github.io/cvilleequity_covid/
- 4: https://data.library.virginia.edu/statlab/
- 5: https://data.library.virginia.edu/
- 6: https://data.library.virginia.edu/training/past-workshops/
- 7: https://doi.org/10.18130/v3-ztey-hn31
- 8: https://www.press.uillinois.edu/books/catalog/75hhf7en9780252035920.html